I feel lonely since my brother passed away
(Questioner) Hello, Sunim.
Hello.
(Questioner) I'm a 15-year-old student.
My brother passed away last year.
Out of everyone in my family,
I talked to my brother the most,
and we had so much in common.
We were very close, at least in my mind.
But now that he passed away,
I'm often all alone at home.
I can no longer ask him
for advice or stories.
I can no longer joke around with him.
It makes me feel so lonely.
Right after his death,
I started getting counseling.
And I also openly communicate
with my family,
so I thought I would feel
better eventually.
But as time passes by,
I always wonder how things would be
different if my brother were around.
I wonder if I would have been stronger
and happier with him around.
There's no reason I shouldn't
be thinking of him, is there?
So I wonder whether I should continue to
live my life longing for my dead brother.
I see. Let's give this student a round
of applause for encouragement. (Applause)
When you're parting with a friend,
if you keep crying and
don't let go of her hands, saying,
"Oh, what am I supposed to do
without you? I'm going to miss you!"
Can the friend leave you swiftly?
She would have trouble
leaving you, wouldn't she?
I fully understand how saddened
you are of losing your brother.
But you keep longing for him
and wishing he were alive.
Let's say that your brother's soul
lives on in the afterlife.
We can't prove whether
soul exists or not, can we?
(Questioner)
Perhaps it exists.
(Sunim) Nobody can say that for sure.
But we generally believe that it exists.
Assuming that it exists, could you call
him back after he had already died?
No, I couldn't.
According to the Buddhist thought,
your brother would be reborn
as a different being. Right?
Yes.
According to the Christian thought,
he would go to heaven.
(Questioner) Yes.
Or go to the Buddhist heaven.
Should he not go there and live happily?
Or should he remain as a ghost
and wander around?
He should live happily.
Yes, he should.
Then, can he do that if you keep longing
for him and calling out to him?
No, he can't.
He can neither leave nor stay.
What does that make of him?
He would become a lonely, wandering soul.
Then who made him become
that lonely, wandering soul?
Me?
Yes. You can miss him all you want,
but you can't make your brother suffer.
If he becomes a lonely soul,
he will suffer too much.
(Questioner) I see.
You are free to miss him, but you have
no right to cause him suffering.
But I can still think of him, right?
(Sunim) You can, but if you do,
he can't leave you.
You can yearn for him, it's your choice.
For example, when you're
parting ways with a friend,
you could hold onto her and sob, right?
But if you do that, can
your friend leave you or not?
(Questioner) She can't.
No, she can't. Even if the friend leaves,
how would she feel leaving you?
She'd feel bad.
It's understandable that
I will miss my friend,
but would it help my friend
if I hold on to her?
(Questioner) No, it wouldn't.
Correct.
Now you understand that what you're doing
doesn't help your brother in any way.
It's only making him suffer.
(Questioner) I see.
Then should I just suffer?
No, you shouldn't suffer. You need
to let him go as soon as possible.
When you part ways with a friend,
if the friend keeps looking back
to you, what do you say?
You say, "hey, we can see
each other again. So go. Go now."
When we leave someone, we tell those
we leave behind to go back inside quickly.
And the other person says,
"don't look back, just go!"
In the same way, what should
you say to your brother?
"Farewell my brother,
have a safe journey."
"Bye, brother." That's it.
That's how you can help your brother.
Would you prefer to send
your brother to heaven?
Or would you rather have him remain
a ghost wandering by your side?
I'd want him to go to heaven.
Then what should you do?
You should let go of him right now.
You need to cut him off from your thoughts.
Tell him, "Goodbye, brother,"
and let him go.
Will you keep hanging
onto him for your sake?
Or will you let him go for his sake?
(Questioner) I should let him go.
Then say it here now.
Try saying, "Bye-bye, brother." Now.
Bye-bye, brother.
(Sunim) Bye-bye.
Bye-bye.
No, you're saying that against your will.
You're saying it because I'm
telling you to. Say it like you mean it.
Say, "Goodbye, my brother,"
and let that be it.
(Questioner) Goodbye, brother.
No, not like that.
It's as if you're saying,
"Farewell, but do come back."
It's like you're saying, "no, thank you,"
but taking it at the same time.
You're saying farewell, but you're telling
him, "how can I live without you?!"
That's not a good send-off.
Say it cheerfully, "Farewell, my brother."
(Questioner) Goodbye, brother.
Do you feel like you let him go?
(Questioner) Ah, I don't know.
Try it again. Let him go.
Really do it for his sake. Truly.
(Questioner) Do I really
have to do it here?
Yes. Even if you do it here, you'll
think of him again when you go home.
But if you can't do it here, then you
definitely won't be able to do it at home.
(Questioner) Goodbye, brother.
You didn't mean that at the end.
You were doing it well,
then you were about to cry.
Say it in a clean, light way.
"Farewell, brother."
Watch me say it. "Farewell, brother."
But you can't do it right now.
Try it again.
(Questioner) Farewell, brother.
Oh my. Why keep holding
onto him like that?
Say, "Farewell, brother. Goodbye."
(Questioner) Just go already, brother.
You don't really like
your brother, do you?
If you really like him,
you should let him go.
Did he bother you much when he was alive?
(Questioner) No, he didn't.
Are you not intentionally trying to get
back at him for bothering you before?
If your brother was so good to you,
you should also be good to him.
You should let him go, "Bye-bye brother."
(Questioner) Goodbye, brother!
Really this time. (Applause)
I would be nice of you
to let him go here right now,
but I don't think you're
even halfway there.
You can't let go with a tone like that.
You should really try letting
him go. Do you understand?
(Questioner) Yes.
Only when you let him go can he
really move on to a good place.
What can you do now to help him do that?
Isn't it your duty to make sure
he moves on to a nice place?
(Questioner) Yes.
Are you trying to send
him off to a bad place?
(Questioner) No, I am not.
Of course not. He can't move on
if you keep holding onto him.
But if you can cheerfully bid him
farewell, you can let him go.
Once you truly let him go,
it's ok to think of him.
Do you understanding?
There's a difference between
remembering him and longing for him.
Remembering him is fine.
But you shouldn't long for him.
That's wanting to bring him back.
(Questioner) In the past, I didn't cry
very much thinking of him.
Even until the middle of
this year, I felt okay.
But after counseling and starting school
again, it has been difficult to control.
I see. If you can't control your feelings,
your brother can't move on.
And you will fall into
depression eventually.
Your mother will worry about you.
Who is sadder for losing him--you or your mom?
Mom is sadder.
Then, you should bid him farewell and
encourage your mom to let him go.
If you're crying every day for him,
your already sad mom becomes
even more miserable.
I've never talked about this anywhere.
(Sunim) You should let him go.
(Sunim) You need to feel
happy again, okay?
(Questioner) Okay.
Try smiling.
I laugh easily.
You're suppressing your
sorrow. Let all of it go.
(Questioner) Yes.
Starting today, do 108 prostrations daily,
and pray for your brother for 100 days.
Every time you prostrate, say,
"Goodbye, brother." Do that 108 times.
How? "Farewell, my brother." "Goodbye."
Do this as you prostrate 108 times.
(Questioner) Okay.
If you do it for 100 days,
he'll really move on to a good place.
(Questioner) My brother was Catholic.
Then, where will he go?
He'll end up in heaven, won't he?
(Questioner) Yes.
You said he'll go to heaven.
I didn't say where he should go.
What did I say? I said you should
wish him to go to a good place.
(Questioner) Yes.
If he's Christian, he'll go to
Christian heaven.
If he's Buddhist, he'll go to
Buddhist heaven.
Each one has his or her own path.
Where he goes is not
that important to you.
What's important is that
he goes where he wants to go.
Not where you'd like him to go.
Wherever it is that he wants to go,
he should go to a good place and quickly.
Do you understand?
(Questioner) Yes, thank you.